Now today's דף daf is קמ"ד, Kuf Mem Dalet, 144, 12 squared.
Okay, we pick up with
the גמרא Gemara right after the משנה Mishna on the bottom of
קמ"ג Kuf Mem Gimmel עמוד ב, Amud Bet, and we just did
this issue about if there was an estate left and there were
older kids and younger children, and תוספות Tosafot seems to really read
it that the younger children are קטנים, katanim, minors, that that seems
to be an important factor. Anyway, so if they increase the value
of the estate, they invest some of its money, they plant, they
do whatever, etc., so it says that we assume if the older
did I say students children, the older children do that, then we
assume that they're doing it on behalf of the whole estate unless
they make some other declaration, even though normally that wouldn't be the
הלכה Halacha if one שותף shutaf let's say were to work the
property of the land of another שותף, shutaf, there'd be some reimbursement
for his efforts or whatever. Anyway, here they're all brothers, we assume
they're doing it on behalf of the whole estate. If however they
make a declaration and they say, look, we're doing this for our
own, you know, for our own sake, the way רשב"ם Rashbam also
adds like we're ready to divide if you're ready, but anyway, but
we're doing this for our own sake, then anything they benefit they
get to accrue the benefit. Now the question is why? Let's say
they're planting the whole land and they harvest the whole land, you
know, or whatever it is, or they invest all the money and
they make 5, 10 percent on all the money, why do they
get to keep the benefit of the part of the estate that
wasn't theirs, you know, just cause they made this declaration? So תוספות
Tosafot says that basically the assumption here is that the others who
are not participating are קטנים, katanim, are minors, and that basically it's
sort of like the קטנים katanim aren't able to do it themselves,
and they're not losing out by the older ones doing the, you
know, doing it. It's not like, hey, you're investing my money, I
can't invest my money. No, if we the older ones wouldn't invest
your money, it would just be laying and not earning anything. So,
you know, you're not losing out, you don't have the opportunity, if
I were a nice guy I'd invest your money for you, okay,
but fine, I'm not a nice guy. Okay, but anyway, but you're
not losing out, you don't have the opportunity to do anything with
it yourself so if I'm making that declaration somehow I'm entitled to
do that. Now תוספות Tosafot also has a תוספות Tosafot also quotes
a תוספתא Tosefta that well although also it's not dealing with the
question about let's say the principal's at risk, but let's bracket that.
תוספות Tosafot quotes a תוספתא Tosefta that they have to make this
declaration in front of a בית דין, Beit Din, and he suggests
that the reason that they have to make it in front of
a בית דין Beit Din is because, you know, it's not totally
fair to the קטנים, katanim, like okay, they're קטנים, katanim, but like,
you know, and maybe therefore the בית דין Beit Din would have
would before they gave the approval for that would basically say, wait,
wait, wait, let's maybe have a assigned an אפוטרופוס apotropos for the
קטנים katanim and maybe have them involved in this investment and in
the whatever. So by saying that they have to do it through
a בית דין Beit Din and get בית דין Beit Din to
sign off on it, it's a little bit more palatable. The קטנים
katanim aren't in a position to do anything themselves, why let the
stuff lay fallow, and they got the approval of the בית דין
Beit Din which means בית דין Beit Din looked into it and
saw that it wasn't reasonable to do to have somebody, you know,
represent the קטנים katanim in this. That's sort of the way תוספות
Tosafot frames it. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
It's reasonable not to make this declaration?
No, no, unless they just don't want to look like money-grubbers, you
know, or maybe they actually do want to do it on behalf
of the estate, they're guy they're good guys. You know, we're all
brothers, you know, of course you'd want to, you know, invest the
money on behalf of the estate.
Because if you don't make this declaration in front of בית דין
Beit Din and you know, even though they've been discussing it amongst
the family...
Yeah, correct,
correct, yeah.
I just want to go back for a very brief moment to
the משנה, Mishna, the word לאמצע l'emtza written in the משנה Mishna
to mean the estate. Yeah, but how does it mean the estate?
Imagine they're all around a circle.
So truly a choreography in a way. Right, it's like a visual,
right.
Yeah, but we're
out between them all.
Yeah, but I think it means like, you know, you sort of
see them all in a circle and like the money is put
in the middle, something like that. But yeah, but it's a good
point to note the sort of geographic nature of that
word. Okay, אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabi Hanina, the גמרא, Gemara, בריה
דרב יוסף בריה דרבא משמיה דרבא. brei de'Rav Yosef brei de'Rava mishme
de'Rava. So this tradition in the name of רבא. Rava. לא שנו
אלא שבח נכסים מחמת נכסים. Lo shanu ela shevach nechasim machmat nechasim.
When is it that we assume if they don't say anything they're
doing it on behalf of the whole estate? If the property increased
on its own internal funds, meaning that you used money from the
estate to hire workers to plant the field, or you took the
money of the estate and you invested it in the stock market,
so that they didn't really do anything, they didn't invest their own
money, they didn't, I mean they invested a little effort to go
hire the workers, but they didn't really invest like a lot of,
of you know, personal effort and no personal money. So in that
type of a case we'll say that they are doing it that
without a declaration it's all on behalf of the whole estate. אבל
שבח נכסים מחמת עצמן, Aval shevach nechasim machmat atzman, but if the
נכסים nechasim increased because of them, them not be the נכסים, nechasim,
them the brothers, the brothers actually used their money, they used their
own money, or they went out into the fields and they planted
it, okay, or they were supervising every single day, they were בועז,
Boaz, they were going every single day and supervising the workers, so
they actually exerted... exerted a serious amount of their own effort or
their own funds, then even without a declaration, we're going to assume
that they're doing it for their own profit. So in that case,
השביחו לעצמן, hishbichu le'atzman, they do it for their own. Of course,
they could say, you know, heck, we know, no, we're doing it
for the behalf of the estate, but there they don't even need
a declaration. The assumption is that with that amount of their own
putting their own money out there or putting their own effort out
there in a serious way, that they're doing it for themselves. Okay,
איני, eini, is that really true? ואמר רבי יוחנן, ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan,
אפילו לא הניח להם אביהם אלא אודייני, afillu lo hiniach lahem avihem
ella udayni, even if their father only left them an אודייני. udayni.
Now, an אודייני udayni is of course what it means, but anyway
we'll go with the רשב"ם. Rashbam. He says it means basically a
cistern, and that you are basically, you know, I don't know, you're
renting out the cistern or you're selling the water from the cistern.
So even if he only left them that, השכר לאמצע, hashachar la'emtza,
they share it. Okay, so now what is the relevance of that?
והא אודייני דמחמת עצמן הוא, veha udayni demachmat atzman hu, an אודייני,
udayni, that's something that, you know, in order to operate it, somebody's
got to be standing there by the cistern and protecting the water
and basically doing the transactions. And notice he said, now why can't
you say, okay, maybe they hired a guy? Because it says all
he left them was the cistern. There's no money in the estate
to hire the guy to operate the cistern. So the only way
this cistern is going to generate income is if one of the
brothers stands there and sells the water and protects it. So why
is that לאמצע? la'emtza? According to you, that's because the brothers themselves
are exerting the effort, and therefore they should be able to keep
the profit. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, שאני אודייני דלנטירותא הוא
דעבידא, shani udayni delentiruta hu de'avida, that's different, that all you have
to do is watch it, דאפילו קטנים נמי מנטרי ליה, de'afillu ketanim
nami mantru lei, and even the minors can watch it. So it
does need, so big deal, what, no, it does need to be
operated, but this goes back, תוספות Tosafot says, remember תוספות Tosafot explains
the reason why you, the older brother, are allowed to work it
and keep the profit for yourself if you make a declaration or
whatever you're investing your money, is because you can say, look, the
minors aren't losing out, otherwise we would just be laying fallow, otherwise
no profit would be earned at all from this. So, you know,
so I'm going to do it and keep the profit to myself,
it's not hurting them. But if the minors can say, wait, true
we're only ten years old, but we can also do it, what
do you mean, let us do it and let us also share
in the profit, right? So we're in a position to do it
even as קטנים. ketanim. So in that type of a case, you
know, you cannot keep it to yourself because you are actually hurting
the minors. Alright, so in that type of a case it would
be לאמצע. la'emtza. But normally if the minors are not in a
position to actually do anything themselves, then if you make a declaration
or it's an implicit declaration because you're investing your own funds, you
get to keep it. Okay, and again, תוספות Tosafot says that this
is all with the approval of בית דין. Beit Din. Except the
problem I guess is that in the case where you're investing your
own funds, you don't need the approval of בית דין. Beit Din.
So there's actually, you could think about it, there could be ways
that you could be pretty deceptive. Like, you could say to yourself,
okay, if I go to בית דין, Beit Din, they're going to
actually appoint an אפוטרופוס apotropos for my minor brothers and they're going
to share in the profit. What I'll do instead is I'll invest
my own money and I'll keep all the profits for myself, you
know, so then you avoid the need of בית דין's Beit Din's
approval. So I don't know, some of the cases don't sound totally
fair, but let's move on. Okay, what?
I was just thinking about it as somebody being
disadvantaged.
No, on the other hand, there are definitely scenarios where like if
you know that nobody's doing anything with the field, it's just laying
fallow and nobody's earning any money. Okay, but again, I guess what
we feel is that there should be something given to the קטנים,
ketanim, like some percentage or whatever of the profit. Anyway, yeah. So
let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. ואם אמרו ראו
מה שהניח אבא הרי אנו עושים ואוכלים השביחו לעצמן. ve'im amru reu
mah shehiniach abba harei anu osim ve'ochlim hishbichu le'atzman.
So one is, we talked about the case that's implicit or whatever
where they invested their own money or effort, but if they or
they make a declaration, even if they're using the estate funds, they
get to keep all the profit. רב ספרא שבק אבוה זוזי. Rav
Safra shavak avuh zuzei.
רב ספרא's Rav Safra's father left him, meaning passed away and left
him as ירושה yerusha money. שקלינהו, shaklinhu, he took the money, עבד
בהו עיסקא avad behu iska and he did business with it. Okay,
now this is going to be considered as a case of שבח
נכסים מחמת נכסים, shavach nechasim machmat nechasim, as a case because he
used the own estate funds and the question is, okay, but I
mean he still did business, so you know that's his own effort.
So the רשב"ם Rashbam says, if you look at the first narrow
line of the רשב"ם, Rashbam, וחשבי ליה שבח נכסים מחמת נכסים הואיל
ואין צריך טורח כל כך אלא לקנות ולמכור. vechashvei lei shavach nechasim
machmat nechasim ho'il ve'ein tzarich torech kol kach ella liknot velimkor.
And you go tell somebody whose whole business is import and export,
yeah what's a big deal, it's just to buy and sell. So
I think the, maybe the best example to think about this as
a parallel would be let's say the stock market, okay? Where it's
not a big deal to call up your stockbroker and to say
buy X number of shares. I mean what you do need is
you need your, you know, the wisdom or the insight or whatever,
the good fortune to make the right types of purchases, right? But
the point is that's not considered to be interestingly like a lot
of טורח. torech. If you're a smart guy and you can see
a good bargain and you can effort to hire good workers rather
than bad workers. Okay, so here what he did was he took
the money, he invested it, he made a profit, that's considered to
be—he didn't make a declaration—it's שבחו נכסים מחמת נכסים, shivchu nechasim machmat
nechasim, so the הלכה halacha should be that the שבח shevach should
be לאמצע. le'emtza. Okay, so let's see what the הלכה halacha is.
And the סוגיא sugya seems to me is creating a continuum, right?
Like the אודייני idney is like nothing, doesn't even—you can sleep on
it, right? Right? So here it might be a little bit more
טרחא, tircha, like you're doing something a little bit more active, but
you could argue that you're really not doing very much. Right, I
mean, everything requires a certain amount, even in the classic נכסים מחמת
נכסים, nechasim machmat nechasim, even if it's like I got it, I
used—I'm not doing anything, I just hired the workers to plant the
field and I hired the foreman. Okay, it required a little intelligence,
taking out some ads, making sure you're hiring the right workers. Exactly.
And that's—well, I don't know, if you walk around and look, that
might be מחמת עצמו. machmat atzmo. Maybe you hired also the foreman.
But the point still is, everything requires effort to get it going,
but seems like that there's a level of minimal effort that is
considered שבחו נכסים מחמת נכסים, shivchu nechasim machmat nechasim, yeah? Right, which
in this case there's not much risk involved, but for other investings,
isn't there—what about the risk involved? Yeah, so that's what I said.
I do not know at all how to deal with the fact
about like what—since when are you—like are you allowed to put the
principal at risk, right?
And let's say, you know, and what happens if you lose all
the money, you have to make it up to your younger brothers?
Like that's completely ignored. I don't know the answer. Okay, so it
says, okay, so אתו אחי, atu achai, so the other brothers came,
תבעוהו בדינא, tavuhu bedina, they brought him to a בית דין, beis
din, and they say, we want our share, שבח לאמצע. shevach le'emtza.
So קמי דרבא, kamei derava, in front of Rava. אמר להו, amar
lehu, he said to them, רב ספרא גברא רבה הוא, Rav Safra
gavra raba hu, Rav Safra's a great personage, right? He's a big
rabbi. ולא שביק גירסיה וטרח לאחרני, velo shavik girseih vetarach leachrinei, he's
not going to take any time away from his learning in order
to be making profit for other people, right? Every minute is precious.
So any minute he's taking away from his learning, it's only to
support his learning, so he clear—he's not in the—he's not in the
business of doing צדקה tzedakah for other people. Right, so I mean,
I—what? So that means—so that means that the same way in the
past if we read using your own money as an implicit declaration,
for רב ספרא, Rav Safra, since there's just an assumption that you're
never working on behalf of the brothers—not because he's stingy or doesn't
give צדקה tzedakah or whatever, but just because like he's got to
do his learning and make his own living and he's got to
prioritize his own, you know, his own living—it's like implicitly he made
a declaration. So of course then the funny thing comes, so then
it shouldn't only apply to like big rabbis who never want to
be מבטל תורה mevatel Torah unless it's absolutely necessary. You would also
apply—what if you had a brother that was a complete stingy person
and he has a track record of completely ignoring his brothers and
not caring about their welfare and letting them starve while he's off
making money? So should we also assume for him it's an implicit
declaration that he's doing it for himself? Like I don't know, but
you know, it's very interesting. Okay. Right, so it is—I would have—I
would have thought the הלכה halacha was the opposite. לא טרח, lo
tarach, right? ולא שביק גירסיה וטרח לאחרני. velo shavik girseih vetarach leachrinei.
So he's being טרח toireach for himself, for himself. He's not doing
it לאחרני. leachrinei. Right, but I'm saying
the other
way,
he
put any טרחא tircha into the
estate?
אדרבה, aderaba,
then he would have to split it with them.
Exactly.
No, אמר להו, amar lehu, no, if they're—אמר להו, amar lehu,
he's saying
to
them, he means—he
means they're losing. I understand that's the פשט, pshat, but I
would
have said
the same
reason for the
opposite.
Right, well, that's why they
brought
him to a דין.
din. But okay, if you look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, the רשב"ם
Rashbam says if like about I don't know where is it—one, two,
three, four, five, about eight lines down, line starts with דומיא dumya
in the narrow lines—he says ושמעינן מהכא דכל היכא דמאן דהו, ushmainan
meihacha dechol heicha deman dehu, כמו רב ספרא, kemo Rav Safra, anytime
you have anybody like Rav Safra, אף על גב דלא אמר לעצמי
אני עוסק כמאן דאמר להו והשביח לעצמו. af al gav delo amar
le'atzmi ani osek keman de'amar lehu vehishbiach le'atzmo. It's like he implicitly
said, not just Rav Safra. Now who's anybody like Rav Safra? Do
I have to be a תלמיד חכם? talmid chacham? Is this really
a bias towards תלמידי חכמים? talmidei chachamim? Or let's say it's just
like I said, somebody who we know never does anything on behalf
of his brothers, always does it for himself, you know, who knows?
Okay, so now, yes.
It seems like the opposite of other stories where there's a higher
ethical standard imposed on—right.
Right. I don't know if this is a question about a—about a
degree
of—it's like—it's not a compromise of ethics. I mean, you're allowed to
say I'm doing it for yourself. It's
completely—I mean, it's nice to, you know, to do it for behalf
of your brothers. But I don't think we were ever suggesting that
if they're saying like we're doing it for ourselves, you know, that
they're doing something that's unethical. You're right, it's not necessarily the most
generous thing. I understand, yeah, I hear the point. I hear the
point. It's a good point. It's a good point. Okay, you're right.
At the end of the day, you're using the money of the
whole estate to enrich yourself, right. It's not just that you're not
giving צדקה tzedakah to your brothers, you know,
it's— Okay, אשה בנכסי
יתמי ההיא אשה דאשבחה נכסים אשבחה לאמצע. Isha b'nichsei yatmi hahi isha
d'ashbacha nechasim ashbacha l'emtza. It's the same הלכה halacha if a woman
does it with the heirs and in the scenario where she also
is an heir to the estate. We'll see how in a minute.
Then same point, if she just does it without saying this is
shared by everybody, if she makes a declaration, she keeps it to
herself. אשה בנכסי יתמי מה עבידתה? Isha b'nichsei yatmi mah avidta? What's
a woman doing taking a portion in the inheritance of the heirs?
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי ירמיה באשה יורשת. Amar Rabbi
Yirmiya b'isha yoreshet. She is an heir. Now what's the scenario? So
the גמרא Gemara leaves it to the רשבּ"ם Rashbam to explain what
the scenario is. So the simplest case is that the person basically
wrote a will and he basically said, let my wife inherit together
with my children. We had that yesterday. So she's effectively an heir,
she's a יורשת yoresha through the instrument of מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat
shechiv mera. Okay, but she's basically an equal participant in the estate.
What I find fascinating and I haven't actually thought this through fully,
gets to how much מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera is duplicating
ירושה. yerusha. We discussed it the other day about like whether the
woman still has her כתובה ketubah liens on the estate. This construct
of תפיסת הבית, tfisat habayit, an estate, does it apply by a
מתנת שכיב מרע? matnat shechiv mera? If I gift my property to
my ten kids in different proportions, right, and with a מתנת שכיב
מרע, matnat shechiv mera, are they... is it all now part of
this corporate entity and estate? It sounds like if you read that
that's this case in the גמרא, Gemara, the answer is yes. So
if I do my wife and my kids, it's all part of...
Let's say I do three strangers from China and my kids. Are
they all now part of the same of this corporate entity called
an estate? Right? Or do we say no, you have that piece
of land, you have that piece of land... Maybe it depends how
I frame it. If I say I'm giving that person piece of
land X, then there's no estate, each person has their own piece
of land or... But if I'm saying John and Fred and Sarah
and my two sons should inherit my entire estate, now there is
this entity called an estate, even though it contains people that are
complete strangers and people that aren't related to me. Right? I mean,
but you hear my question, right? We've been dealing all along with
this idea that there's this entity called the estate. Does that... is
that true when the people who inherit, inherit through מתנת שכיב מרע?
matnat shechiv mera? So the way the רשבּ"ם, Rashbam, one explanation of
the רשבּ"ם Rashbam is, well at least with my wife and kids
the answer would be yes, maybe even with my stranger and kids.
But at least I would think it would be limited, as I
said, to a case where I don't give people individual sections, but
I list a group of people and I say all collectively they
should inherit. So if I do that, then there can be this
estate with these like strangers or these people certainly that aren't all
heirs.
But if you don't see the others what you're saying is that
automatically they used money, so to own money you're using in this
netherland.
Yeah, then this whole thing is irrelevant. If it's not an estate,
if everybody just gets their piece of the inheritance, then they just
have their own money. Okay, now that's one scenario where it was
done through מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat shechiv mera. The other scenario, I'll
just draw quickly, is where it's done through a ירושה yerusha and
here's the story. Okay, here's ראובן Reuven and here's שמעון Shimon and
here's שמעון's Shimon daughter. Okay.
So ראובן Reuven marries his niece. Okay.
Here's their father יעקב. Yaakov.
Okay.
So now יעקב Yaakov dies and he leaves over this estate, okay,
which is now jointly owned by ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. Okay.
They never got around to dividing it, okay,
and then שמעון Shimon died
and so שמעון Shimon died, now she here is a יורשת, yoreshet,
she's now a... well whatever, שמעון Shimon died and then let's say
she's now a joint owner in that estate of יעקב's. Yaakov Okay.
And now ראובן Reuven dies. So now ראובן Reuven dies, so his
kids, right, he has sons, okay,
so his kids... so basically these sons now together with her are
now the heirs to that estate. So, okay, you got it? So
the sons with their mother are the heirs to that estate.
Did שמעון Shimon have to die before ראובן Reuven in order for
that to be...?
No, as long as the estate isn't divided, they're all heirs to
that estate. So תוספות Tosafot has a different scenario.
Are those children her children?
They could, yeah, they could be, but they're also ראובן's Reuven children.
Okay, so what so... Okay,
that's right.
So she's an heir to the estate because of her father and
they're an heir to the estate because of their husband. תוספות Tosafot
has another variation on this because it sounds like he's an heir
because her husband died. In this scenario, she's an heir because her
father died. So תוספות Tosafot has a variation on this that there
are no... I'm trying to remember what's his variation... yeah, there are
no sons, so ראובן Reuven they've got these other brothers, okay,
so in that
case, oh. In this case, he dies and he dies. I don't
know. I'm not gonna figure it out. Anyway, she's a יורשת yoreshet
together with the brothers, you know, that was somehow, but I can't
totally process it.
But okay, you got the idea. Anyway, so it's אישה היורשת. ishah
ha-yoreshet. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
פשיטא.
peshita. So anyway, once we have that scenario, of course it's the
same as the case of older brothers and younger brothers. What difference
does it make? It's all a variation on the same point. No,
מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought,
כיון דלאו דרכה למטרח, keivan delav darchah lemitrach, אף על גב דלא
פירש כמאן דפירש דמי. af al gav delo peireish keman depeireish dami.
Similar like we saw by רב ספרא. Rav Safra. Women don't normally
go out and do business stuff. So if she's going to that
effort of going ahead and doing the business stuff, we're just going
to assume she's doing it on her own behalf because it's so
unusual. Sort of like רב ספרא, Rav Safra, unusual of him to
leave the בית מדרש Beis Medrash that he would not be, you
know, putting himself in this awkward position, you know, except that they're
doing it for, you know, to provide for themselves. קא משמע לן
kama mashma lan that we don't say that, that if you don't
make a declaration, it's for all the heirs. Okay, ואם אמרה, ve'im
amrah, if she says, ראו מה שהניח לי בעלי הריני עושה ואוכל,
re'u mah she-hiniach li ba'ali ha-reini osah ve-ochelet, she's speaking to the
public. She makes the declaration, she keeps it. פשיטא, peshita, that's also
obvious. Once she's made a declaration, of course she should be entitled
to keep it. No, מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might say, כיון
דשביחא לה מילתא, keivan deshvicha lah milta, it's a, on the one
hand, it's rare for a woman to go out and put herself
in the public like that. Okay, on the other hand, if she
does it, she gets a lot of public acclaim in this context.
Maybe not סתם, stam, but in this context, because what are people
going to say? They're going to say דאמרי כטרחה קמי יתמי, de'amri
k'tarchah kamei yasmei, oh my god, you see how amazing, you know,
that Fred's widow is there, you know, that, you know, how Sarah
is? She's going ahead and she's going and she went and she
became a businesswoman and all of this to provide for the heirs.
Okay? So she gets a lot of public acclaim when she does
that. So once that's true, I might say, אחולי אחלה, achulei achlah,
that even if she, that she really wants them to have the,
you know, she's מוחל mochel on it and she wants them to
also share it. Of course, the funny thing is, why would I
say that if she made an explicit declaration? She said, I'm doing
this for myself. But maybe what we're thinking is, that's what she
said, but then once she actually goes out and does it and
she gets the praise once she's actually doing it, then maybe that
overrides her earlier declaration and we should think that she really wants
them to have it. קא משמע לן kama mashma lan that we
don't say that, which makes sense. You made an explicit declaration, you're
going to be framed by that unless you say something otherwise. Okay,
אמר רבי חנינא, amar Rabbi Hanina, says רבי חנינא, Rabbi Hanina,
המשיא, hamasi, thank you, המשיא אשה לבנו גדול בבית קנאו. hamasi isha
livno hagadol bevayit kna'o. Now we're going to switch gears completely.
What? Done with this? Or just, yeah, we're basically done with our
משנה. mishnah. Okay, we're going to a new topic now.
המשיא אשה לבנו גדול בבית קנאו. hamasi isha livno hagadol bevayit kna'o.
If somebody basically is marrying his oldest son and he goes ahead
and he has the wedding in a house, and another גמרא Gemara
says and he has another house to live in, the father, then
we are assuming that he is gifting the house to the son.
Okay, קנאו, kna'o, the oldest son,
the son has קנה koneh the house.
קטן? katan? Yeah. Okay. Now, ודווקא גדול, vedavka gadol, only if it's
his oldest son. ודווקא בתולה, vedavka besulah, and only if the bride
is a virgin, because that's why we assume, I guess, is a
big שמחה simcha that, you know, oldest son, a first wedding for
the woman. ודווקא אשה ראשונה, vedavka isha rishona, also for the son
it's a first wedding. So it's a first wedding for the woman,
it's a first wedding for the son, it's his oldest son. ודווקא
שהשיא ראשון, vedavka she-hisi rishon, and the first son who was married
first.
No, because, you know, you understand, it's like a big deal, you're
finally marrying off your oldest son or whatever, so okay, in that
type of a case we assume that that's what he wants to
do, he wants to gift it. So the גמרא Gemara says, now
now the גמרא's Gemara going to try to possibly limit it. Now
I gave an important limitation that's not in this גמרא Gemara but
another one, that the father has another house in the same town.
Okay, but the גמרא's Gemara going to have other limitations. פשיטא, peshita,
ייחד לו אביו בית ועליה, yiched lo aviv bayit va-aliyah, let's say
the father, it's a house and a second story and they had
the wedding in the lower story of the house. בית קנה עליה
לא קנה, bayit kanah aliyah lo kanah, we're only going to interpret
it for the lower story, not the whole upper story. בית ואכסדרא,
bayit ve-achsandra, let's say there was a house and a portico and
you had and you had the wedding in the house. מהו? mahu?
Do you also get the
portico? שני בתים זה לפנים מזה, shnei batim ze lifnim mize, מהו?
mahu? How about one house inside of another, you know what I'm
saying, like you have access to the inner house through the outer
house? תיקו, teiku, we don't know, fine. מיתיבי, meisivei, now I ask
you on this claim that we assume that this is this huge
gift. ייחד לו אביו בית וכלי בית, yiched lo aviv bayit u-chlei
bayit, let's say
we're having the wedding in this house and I say, here, this
is a house for you for the wedding and here are all
the dishes to use for the wedding party. ייחד, yiched, it's like
you designate. You designate. Meaning, but designate for the sake of the
For the wedding. Okay, you're not saying I'm giving it to you.
So here, the ברייתא Beraisa says the exact reverse. כלי בית קנה.
Klei bayis kana. Oh, so we assume he's gifting the china. Okay,
he says here, look, here's all the plates, you know, go ahead
and it's for the wedding, and the house is for the wedding.
So the plates means you're gifting me all of the china, I
don't have to register. But the house not. בית לא קנה. Bayis
lo kana. So it totally goes against your your פסק. psak. So
אמר רבי ירמיה Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah כגון דהיו אוצרות של אביו מונחים
שם. kegon dehayu otzaros shel aviv munachim sham. No, no, no. That's
a case where there's the father is indicating that he still is
taking keeping possession of the house. Why? His storage is there. Okay.
Now if you say אוצר otzar could sound like the whole house
is basically the basement is filled with his wheat or something. The
גמרא Gemara is going to read that in a very limited terms,
that as long as he's still storing some stuff in the house,
his stuff is in the house, his stuff is still in the
house. Okay, exactly. He's still got his suits in the closet, then
that's a סימן siman that I am not giving my house to
my son.
Okay, right, but that's also when you talk differentiate the כלי kli
and the כלים keilim in the house.
The כלים keilim in the house are not the stuff that the
father is the אוצר. otzar.
No, but meaning if,
yes, I have my son and I say, "Look, here's the house
for the wedding, here here are all the dishes for the wedding,"
but I leave my my suits are still hanging in the closet.
So he gets to keep the the dishes, but he doesn't get
the
house.
But what about even in the case that he just says forget
the dishes, here's the house but he still keeps his suits in
the closet?
Then he doesn't get the house.
He doesn't get anything.
Correct. So now we have made, so and this is a classic
thing, you know, the גמרא Gemara comes out with like this bold
statement, like radical idea, so then the next move is to qualify
it, to push back and to limit its scope. Okay. So,
okay. So, נרדעי אמר אפילו שובכא דיוני. Nardaia amar afilu shuvcha deyonei.
We don't even mean like he's got like a, you know, אוצר
otzar usually means like it's got like my whole house is full
of grain. No. Even if he is only keeping like a pigeon
coop there.
And that's even outside.
Yeah, I guess. I don't even, right, exactly.
רב יהודה בר פפא אמר אפילו אציצא דהרסנא. Rav Yehuda bar Pappa
amar afilu atzitza d'harsana. Even if he's just keeping like a little
bowl of fish hash. Even if I left my my leftover טשולנט
cholent was in the fridge, that shows I didn't give him my
house. Okay, מר זוטרא. Mar Zutra. So now that we're saying this,
we now got the way to avoid the consequence of this whole
פסק. psak. So מר זוטרא אנסבי לברה, Mar Zutra ansvei l'breih, he
married off his son, ותלא ליה סנדלא, v'sala lei sandala, and he
just left his shoes, slippers, hanging on a peg in the house.
They're still my house. Okay. רב אשי אנסבי לברה, Rav Ashi ansvei
l'breih, he married off his son, ותלא ליה אשישא דמשחא. v'sala lei
ashisha d'mishcha. He left a little like a pot, a little bowl
of oil. Okay, it's still my house. Okay, so now we've managed
to completely limit that. What this is doing in this גמרא, Gemara,
I really don't know. I mean, maybe it's talking about one brother
doing on behalf of the estate or talking about a father doing
something of you on behalf of his son, so we read it
as a generous gift, which is how we were reading a brother
not making a declaration and operating on behalf of the estate.
Sure, is this all in the second half or even the first
half?
No, the second half. No, the second half.
So mean, so if he did it in his first house, it's
only half.
It wouldn't work anyway.
Right, I mean he doesn't leave anything.
Yeah, I mean it's an interesting question if I totally if I
totally called up the movers and emptied out the entire house and
then made a wedding for my son in it, like I don't
know, maybe, who knows. אמר מר זוטרא. Amar Mar Zutra. So מר
זוטרא Mar Zutra says, הני תלת מילי שוינהו רבנן כהלכתא בלא טעמא.
Hanei thlas mili shavinhu rabanan k'hilchasa b'lo tama. The following three things
the rabbis made like laws without a reason, like they seem pretty
arbitrary. Now תוספות Tosafos says they are not totally arbitrary, but they
might seem a little arbitrary. Okay. חדא הא, Chada ha, one, the
one we just said, that we're going to assume, oh, you gifted
your son your house. Okay, but it's not totally arbitrary, right? There's
and certainly once we've limited it, there are various indications why we
should see why you would interpret it that way under the right
circumstances. Okay. אידך דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הכותב כל נכסיו לאשתו
לא עשאה אלא אפוטרופא. Idach d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel hakosev kol
nechasav l'ishto lo asaa ela apitropah.
You might remember that if somebody writes over all of his property
to his wife, we assume that he's really doing that not as
a gift, but as a way of making her the executor of
the estate. And that's from a presumption because it's all of his
property, that he wouldn't totally abandon his kids. אידך, Idach, and the
other, דאמר רב מנה לי בידך תנהו לפלוני במעמד שלשתן קנה. d'amar
Rav maneih li b'yadcha tneihu l'ploni b'maamad sheloshtan kana.
I say to Michael, "Michael, that $100 that you owe me, Gloria
is over there. Don't give it to me. Pay, give it to
Gloria."
And that is a way of directly transferring the debt to Gloria.
Because what's the act of קניין kinyan that's effective?
Oh, I mean we didn't actually do it.
We didn't, yeah, it's just we did it with we didn't do
a קניין, kinyan, we didn't whatever, just through our words, right? What
transferred it as an abstract debt, that's like the hardest thing to
transfer. Like money. So I mean it's for efficient business purposes and
sort of, you know, I mean תוספות Tosafos says,
what? What? You could just do a קניין? kinyan? Yeah, but no,
but that's a question is most קניינס, kinyans, you know, it's it's
money, it's a debt, it's hard it's harder to transfer. רב נתן
Rav Noson is this whole thing that he קונה. kones. What? Well
קונה? kones? רב נתן Rav Noson is this
whole thing.
That's when I owe Gloria money. If I owe Gloria $100 and
you owe me $100, then Gloria can just come straight to you.
But I don't owe Gloria anything. Okay? I just, it's Gloria's birthday,
you owe me $100, and I say Michael, Gloria, happy birthday, Michael
owes me $100, he's now going to pay it to you. Okay,
so that is like what transferred it? Right? And it's hard to
transfer an abstract debt.
But the chance I'm suggesting that the transfer might be effected because
the three of them have to be standing.
Yes, that's מעמד שלשתן. ma'amad sheloshtan. It needs all three to be
there. Correct. Okay, let's now turn to page, next mishna. אחים השותפין,
achim hashotfin, the brothers, the partners. Okay, now some, some poskim read
it brothers or partners, but given the context it seems that no,
the point is brothers who are partners, a specific type of partnership.
Like I say, I love this discussion of תפיסת הבית tfisat habayit
because it's the closest halacha gets to the context of a corporation.
It is not a real שותפות. shutfut. There's this abstract entity called
the estate that we're all like equal shareholders in. Okay, so that's
the אחים השותפין, achim hashotfin, these brothers who are partners because they're
all, they've all inherited the estate. Okay, so שנפל אחד מהם לאומנות.
shenafal echad mehem l'umanut. Now, one of them, it's a funny phrase,
נפל לאומנות, nafal l'umanut, because it's actually a good thing. It basically
means one of them is appointed, the Gemara's going to say appointed,
the simple sense of the mishna is one of them gets a
good job, one of them gets hired by Goldman Sachs, okay, and
the answer is נפל לאמצע. nafal l'emtza. Oh, so now as long
as they're still living off the estate, okay, all of his profit
goes to all the brothers. Which is like what? Why? He's making
his own money just because he also has a shared estate doesn't
mean he's not his own person. So the Gemara's going to limit.
He only got
his job because of his family. Ah, so Michael's thinking ahead, maybe
it makes sense in a context where he got his job because
he's part of the family. So that's what the Gemara is going
to say. Okay, so he got it as being seen as a
member of this, the father's family. Now, חלה ונתרפא נתרפא משל עצמו.
chala v'nitrapa nitrapa mishel atzmo. Now, that's on the income side, on
the expenses side, remember we said the estate pays for the, you
know, until you've divided the estate, the estate pays for the food
and the clothing and so on. How about the medical bills? Okay,
so the simple reading of this mishna is the medical bills are
your own. You don't get the medical bills paid by the estate.
All right, but let's see what the Gemara says. תניא, tanya, so
the Gemara says, תנא האי אומנות
לאומנות המלך. tana hai umanut l'umanut hamelech. A baraita we taught that
this, this job that the person got is the king's service. And
the way the Rashbam explains it is is that there would be
families that would get, you know, they'd be on some rotation and
you know, Yaakov's family once a year or once a month or
whatever it is, one of his kids works in the king's service,
it's highly profitable, it's a זכות, zchut, it's not a, it's not
a burden. Okay, so you got chosen because it's your family's turn,
but you're doing it as part of the family. So therefore even
though you're the one who worked,
it could have been any of them.
Could have been any brother, exactly. So therefore everybody shares it. Now
the point still is, do you get paid because you weren't able
to just lie on the beach, you weren't able to go ahead
and do your other job? Like there should be some compensation for
the fact that you know, that you by, you know, but anyway,
but whatever it is, the basic point is it was on behalf
of the family, it was because of the family, so it's all
shared. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught, אחד מן האחים שמינוהו
גבאי, echad min ha'achim sheminuhu gabai, one of the brothers that was
appointed a גבאי, gabai, which does not mean in shul, like some
type of a, you know, some type of a position of authority,
או פולמוסטוס. o polmustos. Now what is the so, so the Rashbam
says that Rabbeinu Chananel says it means a fighter in war, because
do you see a word there that you might be familiar with?
פולמוסטוס, polmustos, פולמוסטוס, polmustos,
polemic. Okay, polemic means to fight or a war. Okay, so some
kind of a king's, you know, some type of an officer or
in war or some type of a, of a king's position, like
some type of a, you know, a civil servant. Okay, אם מחמת
האחים, im machmat ha'achim, if you were appointed because you are seen
as being part of this family,
לאחים, la'achim, meaning it's shared by the whole family. אם מחמת עצמו,
im machmat atzmo, if it was because of no, you had demonstrated
some of your own qualities, you were being seen as an individual,
right, not as just a member of the family, and you know,
you applied for the job, you were interviewed or whatever, then לעצמו,
l'atzmo, then it's for yourself. Of course you know there's always those
funny cases, it's like there you are, you're applying for the job
and somebody says,
oh, Waxman, if your father, that's oh my god, he was like
my best pal back in in at Harvard, oh yeah, we're giving
you the job. Right, so is that מחמת עצמו, machmat atzmo, is
that מחמת האחים? machmat ha'achim? I mean that's the way the world
works, right? So sometimes it's not clear, sometimes it's a mix of
the two, right? So anyway, אם מחמת אחים לאחים פשיטא, im machmat
achim la'achim peshita, if it's for the brothers then the brothers, simple.
gets it and isn't that obvious? No, no. צריכה דחריף טפי. tzricha
d'charif tfei. So that's getting into one of these ambiguous cases. Okay,
you know, yes your family was usually the one that was chosen
and had special standing, but you are a really bright sharp young
man. So מהו דתימא חורפיה גרם ליה, mahu d'teima churfeh garam leh,
let me say that it's the sharpness that caused it? קמשמע לן.
kamashmalan. But how do you know? Meaning what, you know, what do
you mean קמשמע לן? kamashmalan? Maybe it really was חורפיה גרם ליה?
churfeh garam leh? You know, I don't know how you're supposed to
interpret those cases. It does seem like we're saying the default is,
is that we assume that it was because of your connections. Okay,
if your, if it's reasonable to think your connections did it itself,
we're going to attribute it to that and not to you, and
not to, you know, which is probably sadly a lot very true
about how the world works, you know. I think David Sacks once
said, he said, you know, he said, what's this? He says, פרוטקציה
protexia doesn't matter as long as you know the right people.
So anyway, alright.
It's almost like maybe, the way I'm envisioning this is they needed
to get someone from this family, like oh fine we'll just get,
you know, you were going to hire him anyway because you have
a slot for the,
you know, for the internship.
Then he's like, hey, actually this kid isn't so bad. Right. We
lucked out. Right, so we would have hired him anyway. Right, but
what's not answered is the cases that it's not obvious which what
was the dominant what was the deciding factor. And how about a
case of זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem that it really was,
you know, only because of both factors combined? So, you know, we
don't always know how to categorize. Okay. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our
Rabbis taught. אחד מן האחים שנטל מאתיים זוז למסחר ולילמוד אומנות. echad
min ha'achim shenatal matayim zuz lamasher v'lilmod amnut.
One of the brothers took some money, I don't know why it's
why it's being framed as took money. Somehow the estate maybe decided
like, we're going to go ahead and invest in you, you're going
to be, you know, they would usually send one kid off to
become the priest, right? We're going to invest in you, you're going
to be the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham while the rest of us
are going to go are going to go make money. Or the
opposite, take this money, go to that town, learn how to become
a craftsman, learn how to become a blacksmith or whatever, and go
there. Fine. So he's maybe doing it, and he's even doing it
on behalf of the group. Okay. יכולים האחים לומר לו אם אתה
אצלנו יש לך מזונות. yecholim ha'achim lomar lo, im attah etzlenu yesh
lecha mezonot. Listen buddy, while you're living with us we'll pay your
food bill. ואם אין אתה אצלנו אין לך מזונות, ve'im ein attah
etzlenu ein lecha mezonot, if you're not, we won't. Now the question
is, there's two questions. Number one, well one is like why, if
the estate has to provide for his food, why is it any
different? Right? But the other question is like how much is that
factor the fact that, I don't understand two questions two points here.
Is it his initiative that he's going off to this other place,
which gives them more entitlement to say we're not going to pay
for it? You want to go learn, learn in the ישיבה, yeshiva,
you want to go learn something, be my guest, just don't expect
us to pay. What if it was their initiative to send him
off? Also, how much is the two hundred זוז zuz relevant? Is
it because they gave him two hundred זוז zuz as money to
support himself while he's there they don't have to provide him the
food? Let's say he didn't take the two hundred זוז. zuz. Right,
so how's those two factors in the initial setup play off, whose
initiative it was and what's the relevance of the money that he
took with him, is not at all clear. That's not what the
גמרא Gemara is going to focus on.
Is it parallel to the to the payment of the כתובה, ketubah,
let's say they're getting divorced and she moves out she's no longer
under...?
Yeah, but that's specifically how the כתובה ketubah is framed. Here the
basic assumption is, I mean, we there might be that parallel but
we have to explain it cause there that's... right. So but it's
a good it is a good parallel. As long as you're living
here you're supported. Right, that's a good you're right, that's a good
parallel. So that's explicitly
the תנאי t'nai there. Let's see how it's understood here.
Okay, וליתבו ליה כל היכא דאיתא, v'liteivu lei kol heicha d'isa, I
don't understand, if the estate has to support him, let him support
him wherever he happens to be. So the גמרא Gemara says, of
course you have to imagine right, I mean nowadays nothing like this,
I mean not nothing but whatever, this imagine that they're all living
in the house, the father died, and then they're continuing to live
on the father's property and living off the estate. And the exception
is one of the kids isn't there. As opposed to everybody who's
living in four corners of the globe and then a parent dies
and you know then they're all wherever they are. Right so we
live a very different world. Anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says once
the estate has to support him, let him support him even if
he's not living on the estate. So the גמרא Gemara says מסייע
ליה לרב הונא, mesayei lei l'Rav Huna, this supports רב הונא. Rav
Huna. דאמר רב הונא ברכת הבית ברובה, d'amar Rav Huna birchas habayis
berovah, the house is blessed based on the number of people there.
So, which basically means like no, if he were here his presence
would somehow increase the fortune of the house and would mean that
we would have greater income. So you're leaving hurts us. And since
it hurts us we're not we're not going to pay for your
food. So the גמרא Gemara says וליתבו ליה לפי ברכת הבית, v'liteivu
lei l'fi birchas habayis, so okay why don't they just pay his
support but deduct the amount that he would have benefited them by
being present? So the גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי, hachi nami, fine
you're right. So so they do. Now תוספות Tosafos is like what?
How the heck are you supposed to calculate how much he would
have benefited the house? So תוספות Tosafos says well maybe what you
could do is you look at how much did our household income
last year? What's our household income this year that you weren't here?
And clearly that's what we've lost because you weren't here. Of course
to which תוספות Tosafos responds back he says what? You don't think
like some years better and other years are worse and that's all
because he's not here? You know, so תוספות Tosfos therefore suggests a
different read. Of course you could say if you could say if
you could say if the kid was the handyman or the IT
guy in the house and because he wasn't here we had to
call in the repair guy and we had to call in whatever,
that actually would be something you could measure. But anyway, תוספות Tosfos
suggests a very different explanation, which is what I thought. תוספות Tosfos
says it's not that his presence adds income. It's that it's a
lot cheaper to support the פנץ pantz guy if you're paying for
the food for nine guys. Okay, if you're paying so you throw
an extra chicken in the pot, okay? To pay for a separate
guy by himself is a lot greater expense than adding one guy
to a family you're already feeding. And then the גמרא Gemara says
okay, but at least pay his proportional amount. And there's fine, אי
הכי נמי, ee hachi nami, we would pay the extra money we
would spend if he were here. That's a more reasonable read of
how to do the math. Okay, but again the funny thing about
this is, is that it doesn't make it clear what if he
didn't take the 200 זוז? zuz? Was the 200 זוז zuz just
mentioned parenthetically completely irrelevant? What if it was their initiative to send
him off? What is it only if it's his initiative? Right, those
factors are not discussed.
Right, his household income went up then he wouldn't get anything
according to that first read of the גמרא, Gemara, yeah. Okay.
Yeah exactly, he was our bad luck.
They said that like learning תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is like equivalent
as a job.
Right,
oh that's true, the parallel here where it's like אין לי מלמד
את בני אלא תורה, ein li melamed et beni ela Torah, right,
שכל אומנות, she-kol umanut, right. We're going to send you to your
job, right, exactly, yeah I know, that parallel was interesting. Okay, חלה
ונתרפא ונתרפא משל עצמו. chala venitrapa venitrapa mishel atzmo. Now it gets
very interesting. Who has to pay for the doctor bills while they're
all living at the father's home and off of the estate? Right?
And by the way, right, this is why, and I mean I
think the analogy to the widow is good. Again, if you think
about it in these, you know, pre-modern terms, that they're all living
on the property, then you can understand like maybe the estate should
be paying my doctor's bill. I mean the estate is paying my
food bill and my clothing bill, right, as until we've divided the
property and gone our own way, we're seen as all members of
the estate. So if that's true, so let it pay my doctor's
bill. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so but the משנה Mishnah says no. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: שלח רבין משמיה דרבי אילעא, shlach Ravin mishmei
de-Rabbi Ila'i, so רבין Ravin said in the name of רבי אילעא
Rabbi Ila'i from ארץ ישראל: Eretz Yisrael: לא שנו אלא שחלה בפשיעה.
lo shanu ela she-chala bi-fshia. When is it that the estate won't
pay for your medical bill? When you were to blame. You know,
you weren't following doctor's orders, you know, you were who knows what
you were doing,
okay? But באונס, be-ones, if you just got like a whatever you
couldn't do anything about it, you got cold, what are you supposed
to do? Okay or whatever you got, so there ונתרפא מן האמצע.
venitrapa min ha-emtza. Then it's going to be supported by the entire
estate.
You said you said you went skiing and not like but you
still could have had somebody knock into you on the slopes.
Right, so that's true, not every... right. So how do you define
פשיעה? pshia? Like, you know, that's a good point.
I mean you being on the slopes in
the first place is dangerous. Right, I mean you could have said,
yeah. But let's say somebody knocked into you, you went skiing, you
were going down and you broke a leg, you know, just on
your own on your own, you know, maybe at the moment of
breaking your leg you weren't being negligent but the whole decision to
go skiing was your decision. So I don't know how to measure,
what is that line? That's always the question. I understand. I understand.
Okay. So now היכי דמי בפשיעה? heichi dami bi-fshia? What's negligent? כי
דרבי חנינא. ki de-Rabbi Chanina. דאמר רבי חנינא, de-amar Rabbi Chanina, הכל
בידי שמים חוץ מצינים
ופחים, hakol biyedei shamayim chutz mitzinim u-pachim, famous line. Everything is in
the hands of heaven, meaning everything that happens to people when things
happen to you, it's all
באשערט, bashert, okay? So you know, whatever, I got...
well except except for cold and heat, that's a פחים pachim could
also mean like a pit, like if you go out and you
don't watch where you're walking and you fall down a pit, okay,
or you go out without clothes on, so that is not divinely
ordained. That's because you're being stupid. You're not watching where you're going
and you're going without your clothes on, without whatever, without a coat
on, שנאמר צינים פחים בדרך עקש, she-ne'emar tzinim pachim be-derech ikesh, you
know, cold and פחים pachim again probably means a pit but it
could also mean תוספות Tosfos suggests that it means heat. Oh I
don't know, heat by פחם. pacham. Oh maybe, oh that's good. Oh
פחם. pacham. Oh that's interesting, I didn't think I wasn't realizing that.
Okay, but anyway I'd rather read it as cold and a pit
because you can totally see like walking into a pit and not
watching where you're going, potholes. Okay, those are those are in the
path of the of the perverted one. שומר נפשו, shomer nafsho, the
one who guards himself, ירחק מהם yirchak me-hem knows how to keep
away from them. So, you know, you can have bad things happen
to you not because it's all באשערט bashert but because you're just
being negligent.
So then getting the cold is something...
if you went out without a coat in the middle of a
snowstorm. Okay, but a normal cold would be an אונס, ones, okay?
But תוספות Tosfos also says something וגנבי? ve-ganvei? Right? What? What's this?
הכל בידי שמים חוץ מצינים פחים,
hakol
biyedei shamayim
chutz mitzinim pachim, פירש ר"י וגנבי אלא עלמא. peirash Ri ve-ganvei ela
alma. Yeah.
No
no, meaning that's not the צינים ופחים. tzinim u-pachim. The things that
are are בידי שמים biyedei shamayim and are not... your own fault
is if a lion attacks somebody or somebody is robbed, right? That's
not their own fault. Okay, but meaning if it wasn't your fault,
it was מן השמים. min ha-shamayim. But if you were negligent, it's
because you did it. Okay, that's the basic point. Anyway, an important
תוספות Tosafot by the way that limits this is תוספות Tosafot says
this is really interesting. If you look at תוספות Tosafot חלב ונסרפה...
chalav ve-nisrafa... what?
The other phrase is the כוס של ברכה. kos shel bracha.
כוס של ברכה, kos shel bracha, that's a different point. Okay. If
you look at תוספות Tosafot חלב ונסרפה, chalav ve-nisrafa, תוספות Tosafot says
דתניא di-tanya בתוספתא be-tosefta במה דברים אמורים be-meh devarim amurim ברפואה שיש
לה קצבה. bi-refuah she-yesh lah kitzvah. When is that that we say
that it's you know that you have to pay for it yourself
if you're negligent? If it's finite, okay? It's like, okay, here's a
doctor bill for the broken leg. Okay, אבל aval ברפואה שאין לה
קצבה, bi-refuah she-ein lah kitzvah, but if it was something that was
ongoing, you know, somebody needed regular dialysis, okay? So הרי harei or
whatever, you know, cancer treatment, הרי היא בכלל מזונות ויסרפו מן האמצע.
harei hi bi-khlal mezonot vi-yisrefu min ha-emtza.
So that's considered like food and therefore like you know ongoing the
same way you gotta have food, this person needs food and they
need medicine and they need regular treatments. So that's like ongoing, it's
not like an acute thing, it's a chronic thing, and therefore that's
you know supported by the estate. Then תוספות Tosafot says well one
minute, but didn't we learn earlier that you know you can't say
I have higher food needs than my brothers, that we all have
equal payments? So תוספות Tosafot says fine, that's by food needs, you
know. You can't say oh I eat more than my brothers give
me more money. But by medical needs actually if somebody has ongoing
medical needs that's always paid by the estate. Now the interesting thing
is the גמרא Gemara says that the only thing that wouldn't be
paid by the estate would be negligence. So does that mean that
if somebody was negligent and that led to to something chronic that
that's paid by the estate? That's funny. Once you're negligent, you're negligent.
Why isn't it your own? So I don't really understand... I understand
the difference between chronic and acute, and chronic is seen as a
type of מזונות. mezonot. But once the גמרא Gemara limits it to
cases of negligence, which are your own responsibility, I'm not sure how
this would play a role.
But maybe maybe תוספות Tosafot could make the case, right? That that
it's... that exactly that. If you're negligent as chronic then they won't
pay for it. You're saying that everyone's agreeing you do pay for
it?
Yeah, תוספות Tosafot seems to say if it's an אונס oness the
estate always pays for it. And if it's פשיעה peshiah the estate'll
pay for it if it's chronic. Like why does that make sense?
Okay. עיין
שם... ayen sham... okay, let me just check the... okay, באונס דהכא
אין חילוק בין אין לה קצבה ליש לה קצבה. be-oness de-hakha ein
chilluk bein ein lah kitzvah le-yesh lah kitzvah. Right, if it's an
אונס oness it doesn't matter chronic or acute. But if it's a
פשיעה peshiah and chronic, so all of a sudden I was I
was totally negligent and because it's chronic the estate's going to pay
for it? I don't know exactly how to make sense of that.
Okay, you said you were reading חלב, chalav, right? חוץ מקיצים ופחתים?
chutz mi-kotzim u-pachtim? מה זה הכל? mah zeh ha-kol?
I wasn't reading that תוספות Tosafot right now at all, I was
reading the חלב chalav תוספות. Tosafot. I was talking about about paying
for chronic versus acute illness.
A lot of good תוספות.
Tosafot. There's a lot of good תוספות. Tosafot. I used my discretion
as a teacher to decide which one to read. Okay. Thank you.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, next משנה. mishnah. האחים
שעשו מקצתן שושבינות בחיי האב. ha-achim she-asu miktzatan shoshvinut be-chayei ha-av. Okay,
now the point would be somebody would get married, okay, and the
practice would be that oh, you know,
somebody my son's... one of my friends is marrying off a son.
So I'm going to go ahead and some of the close friends
go and they bring gifts, and they bring שושבינות shoshvinut and they
be משמח mesameach with the חתן, chassan, and then you know maybe
I'm doing... because his son's getting married and when my son gets
married, he now has an obligation to repay the favor, okay, and
to similarly bring bring the same gift and be משמח. mesameach.
So the brothers, some of them while the father was alive, they
went and they were the ones that were sent to represent the
family when ראובן Reuven or ראובן'ס Reuven's son got married. Okay. Now
the father died, and now the oldest son of the family who
the father died is getting married. Okay. When the present is brought
back, okay, does it go just to the son? It's paying back
for when the family was represented, when the father's family was represented
when the father was alive. So now when it's coming back, if
the father had still been alive, essentially it would be a gift
to the father. Okay. But now it's coming back and the son
is getting married, is it a gift to the son or is
it a gift to the estate?
So it says: Is this from the estate or from the estate
that it should then the reciprocal then go back to the estate
universe and be divided?
In other words, is it just... wait a minute. Wait a minute,
here's the dad. Okay? Here are his sons. One's leg, whatever, fine.
Here are his sons,
okay? Okay, and here's this guy and whatever, his son is getting
married. All right? מזל טוב. mazel tov.
Fine.
Okay, anyway, so he says hey guy, go bring the שושבינות. shoshvinut.
So he goes ahead and he brings the שושבינות. shoshvinut. Got this
little present.
And the term שושבינות shoshvinut refers to the gift itself or the
presence of the guest, the people?
Both, like the שושבינות... shoshvinut... Yeah, but it also refers to the
present. So he goes and he brings that present representing the family.
Okay? Now the father dies and now it's this kid's turn to
get married, okay? And now here he is, he's shown himself a
nice guy, like he's getting married. Okay. So now this family sends
the שושבינות shushbinos back. Okay? They had to reuse gifts.
Well, yeah, that's it. It's regifting. Okay, so anyway, if that meant,
if the father were alive, that would be seen as being the,
as being gifted back to the father. The father's dead. Is this
being gifted to the son? Or is it being gifted to the
family? Because when the son brought it, he was representing the family.
Family represents the, what's left of the father is the estate. Yeah,
it should go back to the estate.
Yeah, so that's what it says. וחזר שושבינות חזר לאמצע. v'chazar shushbinos
chazar l'emtza. It goes back to the middle. שושבינות נגבית בבית דין.
shushbinos nigbis b'veit din. That's a real debt. So that's just some
like money owed to the estate. It doesn't matter that it's the
son getting married, it's not his gift, it was money owed to
the estate.
Is that really true? Wow, so they can have a legal case
then?
Exactly. That was seen as like legally binding. אבל השולח לחבירו כד
יין וכד שמן אין נגבין בבית דין מפני שהן גמילות חסדים. aval
hashaleach l'chavero kad yayin v'chad shemen ein nigvin b'veit din mipnei shehen
gemilus chasadim. If somebody goes ahead and it wasn't a חופה, chuppah,
okay, and somebody was just sending like, you know, when the father
was alive, it wasn't a חופה, chuppah, it wasn't שושבינות, shushbinos, he
just sent, he had his son go and deliver like, you know,
some gifts. It was, I don't know what it was, it was
חנוכה, Chanukah, go bring over some wine and oil, you know, to
our friend. Okay? And then the father is dead and then this
guy sends it back to the person who delivered the wine and
the oil. So that because that is not a debt to the
estate and there's not that same formal obligation, that would be read
as a gift. Even though clearly socially it was sort of a
way of reciprocating a kindness, since it was given to this person,
it would be his and it would not be the estate's. Okay?
So if a friend went to Florida and sent back to the
house a box of grapefruit addressed to one of the kids.
Right.
Right. Sam here brought the wine and oil on חנוכה Chanukah as
a gift representing the household, but it was just סתם stam a
gift. Happy חנוכה. Chanukah. Right. And then, and then he gave it
to this family, and then the father dies and next חנוכה Chanukah
they send back to Sam a gift. So that's Sam's gift. That's
not the family's gift. Even though clearly it was in a form
of reciprocation, it's still, it was addressed to Sam and it's Sam's
gift. Okay, we'll end here for today.